<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An epistle to the people called Quakers emitted by Mr. Robert Rich; who arrived at London from the Barbadoes the ninth day of September, 1679, and departed this life the sixteenth of November following.</title>
            <author>Rich, Robert, d. 1679.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57213</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1355</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28476</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10603847</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10603847</idno>
            <idno type="VID">45368</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57213)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45368)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1408:51)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An epistle to the people called Quakers emitted by Mr. Robert Rich; who arrived at London from the Barbadoes the ninth day of September, 1679, and departed this life the sixteenth of November following.</title>
                  <author>Rich, Robert, d. 1679.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>11 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>To be sold by Francis Smith,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:45368:1"/>
            <p>AN EPISTLE To the PEOPLE called QUAKERS, Emitted by Mr. ROBERT RICH, Who arrived at <hi>LONDON</hi> from the BARBADOES the Ninth day of <hi>September,</hi> 1679, and departed this Life the Sixteenth of <hi>November</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year 1680, to be ſold by <hi>Francis Smith</hi> at the Elephant and Caſtle in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> a little below the Royal Exchange.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:45368:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:45368:2"/>
            <head>An Epiſtle for the moſt pure Amity and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity in the Spirit Life and Love of God, in all ſincere-hearted Souls amongst the People called <hi>QUAKERS.</hi> And as to them, ſo unto all; or any other Sort or Sect of People that own and follow the Light of Chriſt Jeſus, wherewith every one is enlightened, <hi>ROBERT RICH</hi> ſendeth Greeting in our Lord God E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting. <hi>Allelujah.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IN the Year 1666, feeling the Babe of Grace (the Word in the Heart) to wax ſtrong in the Love of God ſhed a broad in my Heart, I ſent to the Poor of your People <hi>Thirty pounds;</hi> which after ſome of your Leaders had received, (to wit, <hi>John Bolton, Gerard Roberts,</hi> and <hi>Amos Stoddard</hi>) and given under their hands accordingly, 'twas denied to be received; and about a Year after returned to me again, with many evil opprobrious Names; which makes me ſay, That <hi>I went to my Own, but my Own would not receive me, but ſold me into</hi> Aegypt (by their many falſe Reports;) And poor <hi>Joſeph</hi> found no greater Enemies than his Brethren were. Nevertheleſs the Lord my God did not forſake me, but found me out in the Innocency wherewith he had cloathed me, and appeared to me in all my ſtraits, and was my Strength, my joy, and Crown of Glory; and at length brought me forth of Priſon to ſtand before Princes, aſſiſting and carrying me with much Courage, and through great Oppoſition, to bear and finiſh my Teſtimony to Chriſt in the Saints. And being caſt out from my Brethren, the Lord my God took me up, and became my Teacher under whoſe Teachings I felt more of the Love of God, and increaſed more in knowledg of the Things of God, than when I ſat under the Teachings of Men; by whoſe Teachings I grew in Wiſdom and in Stature, unto the meaſure of a perfect Man in Chriſt Jeſus; then I came to know, that out of <hi>Egypt</hi> God called his Son, to whom he hath given, not only the <hi>Heathen,</hi> but the whole World for his Poſſeſſion and Inheritance. In which Spirit of the Son, I call to mind the ſweet Union and Communion I had with the <hi>Quakers,</hi> when they preached Chriſt the Light in every one that cometh into the World, the way to God the Father of Lights; which Light ſprang up ſo ſtrongly in my Heart, that (with St. <hi>Paul</hi>) it ſtruck me down to the Ground, where I felt the Root of the Matter in my ſelf, ſo that I needed no Man to teach me; but as the Unction, that ſmall grain of Muſtard-Seed grew to a great Tree, on whoſe Body did hang all my Sins, my Weakneſſes and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities; which Seed of the Kingdom begot in me a new Heart, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:45368:3"/>Placed within me a right Spirit, the Spirit of Wiſdom and Underſtanding, fill'd with the Love of God. <hi>Allelujah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the day when the People called <hi>Quakers</hi> were ſmall in their own Eyes, I dearly loved them; who did not only preach Chriſt the Truth and Light in every one, but with much boldneſs and courage, and through great Perſecutions, defended the ſame, living in much Love and Amity one with another, (which to me was a moſt lovely ſight to ſee); till there came to be a difference between <hi>J. N.</hi> and <hi>George Fox;</hi> then <hi>G. F.</hi> by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his Enmity and Self-exaltation, envied and perſecuted <hi>J. N.</hi> and begat a moſt bitter wrathful Spirit in all his Friends againſt <hi>J. N.</hi> and all that ſtood by him in his ſufferings. Thus <hi>G. F.</hi> was the Father that begat all thoſe Diviſions, Rendings, and Tearings that were then amongſt the <hi>Quakers,</hi> (and ſince to this very day); which with great violence laſted till <hi>J. N.</hi> took all the blame on himſelf, and made himſelf of no reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who was circumciſed in Heart and Soul; in which Circumciſion he lived and died, a true <hi>Iſraelite</hi> indeed.</p>
            <p>But <hi>G. F.</hi> and his Party continued acting in another manner of Spirit; for I have ſeen thoſe pull, hale, and carry out of their Synagogue at the <hi>Bull and Mouth,</hi> one <hi>Richard Freeman;</hi> and the chief in this work was <hi>John Bolton,</hi> with divers others. At this time I perfectly ſaw, that God had di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided in <hi>Jacob,</hi> and ſcattered in <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and that a ſeparation was making betwixt the Precious and the Vile amongſt the <hi>Quakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And was it not the ſame bitter perſecuting Spirit in <hi>G. F.</hi> that writ a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>J. Perrot</hi>'s Book, called <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity and Amity?</hi> for did not <hi>G. F.</hi> ſay, <hi>This Book was writ with</hi> Cain's <hi>Spirit?</hi> crying againſt his Sottiſhneſs and Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; affirming, That a Cloud had compaſſed him, that he went in the way of the falſe Prophets, that his Spirit would give up the Children of God to Perſecution. Further alleadging, that <hi>J. P.</hi> is one of <hi>Ham's</hi> Stock, and that his groſs Lies proceeded from a deviliſh helliſh Spirit, and that <hi>none that are in the leaſt Truth, will believe him;</hi> and that he is a Liar and Deceiver. And the great Offence <hi>G. F.</hi> takes at this Book, is, that <hi>J. P.</hi> owns the Spirit of God's Grace and Light to be in <hi>Presbyterians, Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, Anabaptiſts, Seekers,</hi> and others; alſo that he hath Unity and Amity with all that walk therein; the which <hi>G. F.</hi> denying, and calling it <hi>a Lye,</hi> &amp;c. plainly ſhews, he is an Enemy to all that will not bow down to him, and call him Maſter, or Father of their Spirits; and that he is turned from the Faith once delivered to the Saints; and that he is removed to another Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel than what at firſt himſelf had preached; and alſo writ againſt <hi>J. P.</hi> that he was like a Dog, ſnarling and biting ſuch as are in the Life of Truth, and ſo like a Dog thinks he will die This and much more hath
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:45368:3"/>
               <hi>G. F.</hi> writ againſt <hi>J. P.</hi> purſuing and hunting him (as <hi>Saul</hi> did <hi>David</hi>) like a Partridg on the Mountains, from Country to Contry, from Region to Region, and from City to City, whitherſoever he went, theſe venemous, Arrows were ſhot againſt him.</p>
            <p>At this time I perfectly ſaw a Star fall from Heaven, called <hi>Wormwood,</hi> or the <hi>Dragon</hi>'s <hi>Tail,</hi> with which he drew to the Ground a third part of the Stars of Heaven; then I ſaw a War in Heaven, (a Religious War) the <hi>Dragon</hi> againſt the <hi>Lamb; Michael</hi> and his Angels fought againſt the <hi>Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon</hi> and his Angels. Which bitter Spirit of the <hi>Dragon,</hi> did write or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite <hi>John Bolton</hi>'s Book, printed 1670, intituled, <hi>Judas and his Treachery,</hi> &amp;c. In which Book, he ſaith, <hi>The thirty pounds</hi> Robert Rich <hi>ſent to the Poor amongſt the</hi> Quakers, <hi>was the price of Blood, and</hi> Judas <hi>his Treachery; That</hi> Robert Rich <hi>is a Vagabond on the Earth, one that hath not an Habitation in the Living God; That he is a Contender againſt God's Bleſſed and Holy Way, the Way of Life, with whom</hi> Robert Bacon <hi>is joined; That they were Idolaters, and judged them to be the Whoriſh Spirit, and that the Myſtery of Iniquity, in</hi> R. R. <hi>and</hi> R. B. <hi>was brought forth to open view.</hi> And all along his Book is full of the like Expreſſions, not only againſt <hi>R. R.</hi> and <hi>R. B.</hi> but the ſame Rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Accuſations are alſo againſt Innocent <hi>J. N.</hi> and <hi>J. P.</hi> and for no Evil ſaid or done againſt any one of them, as in their own Conſciences they well know. To all which Railing Accuſations, <hi>R. R.</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Lord rebuke thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>About the ſame time another Book was writ againſt <hi>R. R.</hi> and <hi>R. B.</hi> by <hi>Ger. Roberts, Geo. Whitehead,</hi> and <hi>E. H.</hi> intituled, <hi>Impudency and Ranteriſm rebuked;</hi> in which they call the Spirit of <hi>R. R.</hi> which ſent Thirty pounds to their Poor, <hi>A drunken ranting Spirit, a fained Love;</hi> and the Gift they call <hi>Cain</hi>'s <hi>Sacrifice, Balack</hi>'s <hi>Reward,</hi> and <hi>Balaam</hi>'s <hi>Wages, Judas</hi>'s <hi>Oblation,</hi> and a <hi>Superſtitious Idolatrous Gift.</hi> Alſo that <hi>R. R.</hi> is <hi>a wandring Star, a ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging. Wave of the Sea;</hi> that <hi>he is a Sow wallowing in the Mire, a Dog caſting up his Vomit;</hi> that <hi>he is that Fool, which ſaith in his Heart, there is no God; and bray a Fool in a Mortar, and he will never be the wiſer; and that this folly hath bin with him ever ſince the days of</hi> J. N. All this, and much more, for nought elſe than for <hi>R. R.</hi> his Gift to the Poor of their People. Which Language let <hi>G. F.</hi> and his Friends well conſider whether it proceeded from the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the Lamb, that loves Enemies, or from the Dragon, that caſts his Floods after the Man-Child to devour Him, who is the only begotten of God in the Saints; He muſt rule and reign, though <hi>G. F.</hi> and his Men of War ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo much rave and rage: I ſay, that the only begotten of God, by the overſhadowing of the Holy Ghoſt in the Saints, the Virgin Daughter of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> whoſe Name is <hi>Immanuel,</hi> muſt ſurely rule and reign. Even ſo, <hi>Amen. Allelujah.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:45368:4"/>
            <p>What had you againſt <hi>J. N.</hi> more than that God had taken away his Judgment from him, and then led him into the Wilderneſs, to be tried and tempted by <hi>G. F.</hi> and others, and to ſuffer by that Spirit that then ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in the Children of diſobedience? who in all meekneſs and patience did bear and ſuffer the enmity and cruelty of all his Perſecutors, as a good Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample.</p>
            <p>And what had you againſt <hi>R. R.</hi> more than that he ſtood by <hi>J. N.</hi> in his Sufferings, and for pulling off his Hat at the Command of the Lord, as a ſign of Love to them that underſtood that ſign better, than if he had ſaluted after your mode and faſhion in giving the Hand? Alſo that he pulled off his Hat, which was to teſtify that the Hat might be made an Idol, hoth in keeping it on, and in pulling it off?</p>
            <p>And what had you againſt <hi>J. P.</hi> more than for owning the Light of Chriſt in <hi>Presbyterians, Independents, Baptiſts, Seekers,</hi> and others, even in all that believed in it, and followed it? And is not the Light of Chriſt in every one, the Enſign, to gather together all of every Sect and Nation, thoſe that follow it, into Unity with the Lord, and Amity one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? And why was <hi>G. F.</hi> ſo bitter againſt <hi>J. P.</hi> for declaring, that no ſuch beggarly Element as the Hat off or on, is any part of God's Worſhip? And if <hi>G. F.</hi> muſt be obeyed in theſe things, rather than the Light of Chriſt in our ſelves; whether then <hi>G. F.</hi> and his preſcribed and impoſed Forms, be not the greateſt Idol that ever was ſet up by a Profeſſing People? let the Witneſs of God in every one be Judg.</p>
            <p>I have lately read a Manuſcript, ſubſcribed <hi>George Fox,</hi> writ to all that would know what thoſe People called <hi>Quakers</hi> are, and ſhewing their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periences which they have ſeen, and gone through, to Prieſts and Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors: Which Paper contains fifty Paragraphs.</p>
            <p>In the firſt and ſecond <hi>G. F.</hi> ſaith, <hi>We thought it a hard thing for</hi> Cain <hi>to kill Righteous</hi> Abel; <hi>but when we look'd within our ſelves, we ſaw that envious wrathful Man that ſlew every appearance of God within, and ready to ſlay the Righteous without.</hi> Then <hi>G. F.</hi> goes on, ſpeaks againſt <hi>Adam</hi>'s Fall, and againſt <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Brethren, for ſelling of him into <hi>Egypt</hi> &amp;c. and tells Prieſts and Profeſſors, <hi>That if they look within, they ſhall find this Nature in themſelves.</hi> And I tell <hi>G. F.</hi> that he need not go ſo far to ſeek this evil Nature in Prieſts and Profeſſors. Let him look but within himſelf, and conſider his own Actings againſt his Innocent Brethren, and he will find <hi>Cain</hi>'s Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <hi>there,</hi> and <hi>Cain</hi>'s Sin to lie at his <hi>own Door,</hi> and will know him that ſold <hi>Joſeph</hi> into <hi>Egypt,</hi> &amp;c. And this Spirit was the cauſe of <hi>G. F</hi>'s own Fall, who was once an Angel of Light, and had a place in Heaven, but is fallen from thence like Lightning, and is now become an Angel of the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:45368:4"/>Bottomleſs Pit, where he rules and governs over all that have not their Names written in the Lambs Book of Life, continuing their forms of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, their long Preachings and long Prayers from the Comprehenſion of Truth, but not with the Life and Power thereof. Thus ye ſuffer that Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>Jezebel,</hi> which calls her-ſelf a Propheteſs, (by good words and fair Speeches) to ſeduce and deceive the Innocent among you, keeping them always learning, but can never come to the Knowledg of the Truth as it is in Jeſus, unleſs they ceaſe from Man's Teachings, and come to the Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of God in themſelves, which alone truly teacheth the way to Life and Salvation. <hi>Allelujah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have alſo read a Teſtimony from the Brethren, met at <hi>London</hi> the third Month 1666, ſubſcribed by eleven of your Miniſtery. Alſo from a Meeting at <hi>Briſtol,</hi> the <hi>27th</hi> day of the <hi>7th</hi> Month 1669, ſubſcribed by 36 Perſons. Alſo from a Meeting at <hi>Ellis Hooks,</hi> the <hi>12th</hi> of the <hi>4th</hi> Month 1677, againſt <hi>John Wilkinſon</hi> and <hi>John Story,</hi> ſubſcribed by 66, moſt of the Miniſtery. All which in general contain, very bitter Cenſures, and high Condemnations againſt many of your own People, who have divided from the Body of Friends, (ſo called by your ſelves) wherein you teſtify, <hi>That thoſe ingaged in the Spirit of Separation, ought not to have any Rule or Dominion in the Church of God, whereof the Holy Spirit that was poured forth upon you,</hi> (as you ſay) <hi>hath made you Overſeers.</hi> But your Fruits will make you more manifeſt than your Words. Alſo, <hi>That all that are joined to that Spirit of Separation, who ſtand not in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity with your Miniſtry, their Judgments ought not to be regarded amongſt Friends.</hi> And further, <hi>You declare your ſelves the Witneſſes and Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchangeable Truth, and the Elders of the Church of God, who of right (having kept your Habitations in the Truth) ought to judg of things which differ, and this your Judgment to ſtand good and valid amongſt Friends a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all that oppoſe it.</hi> Alſo, <hi>that if any pretending to be of your Memberſhip, will not admit to be tried, in caſe of Controverſy, by the Elders and Members of this your Body, but oppoſe it, (as the Judgment of Man) you then teſtify in the Name of the Lord againſt them, that he or ſhe, with all thoſe that countenance theſe Refuſers, are to be rejected, as joined in one with Infidels and Heathens.</hi> Theſe (together with <hi>G. F</hi>'s Paper in vindication of Preſcriptions, dated the <hi>4th</hi> Month 1678) impoſing upon the Conſciences of Men; as alſo the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Invectives againſt <hi>John Wilkinſon</hi> and <hi>John Story,</hi> both importing the ſame Spirit of Dominion and Rule over the Conſcience, (which is the proper Heritage of God) I have both ſeen, well-weighed, and conſidered; and while I contemplate your preſent State, by comparing it with the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples with which you were firſt inſpired, I cannot but take up that Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation concerning you, which the Prophet of old did concerning <hi>Iſrael,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:45368:5"/>How is the Mighty fallen? How is the Gold become dim? the fine Gold how is it changed? Even the Sea-Monſters draw out the Breaſts, and give ſuck to their young Ones, but the Daughters of my People are become cruel, like the Oſtrich in the Wilderneſs.</hi> O let it be timely conſidered by you; how degenerate you are grown from that Love, Meekneſs, and Simplicity to which you at firſt pretended. Are not you the Men that have in your Doctrine exalted the Meaſure of God in all Men, as the only Guide and Director, in that to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide, and by it to be led, and not by any outward Preſcriptions or Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions whatſoever? And are not you the Men that now not only impoſe and preſcribe on others, but alſo condemn and cenſure your Innocent Brethren as <hi>Heathens</hi> and <hi>Infidels,</hi> becauſe in Conſcience they cannot ſubject them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves under the Yoke of your Preſcriptions? Are you ſo preſumptuous, as to conclude all Knowledg and diſcerning in the Things of God, and all Spiritual Judgment is given into your Hands, that you uſurp the Keys of the Kingdom, and will let none in, but thoſe who ſtand in conformity to your carnal and literal Impoſitions? Is <hi>G. F.</hi> and the Body of his Friends, of greater Authority than <hi>Peter,</hi> (who was an Elder and Pillar of the Church?) whom nevertheleſs <hi>Paul</hi> withſtood, becauſe he did not walk up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly according to the Truth of the Goſpel, but endeavoured to compel the <hi>Gentiles</hi> (who had their Law within themſelves) to live after the manner and form of the <hi>Jews,</hi> whoſe Law ſtood much in outward Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation from the Letter, as doth <hi>G. F</hi>'s Comely Order. And are <hi>G. F.</hi> and his Friends, ſo bold and daring, as to condemn the Generation of the Juſt, that went before you in other paſt Ages, under their various Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, (and all thoſe Worthies in our-preſent Time, who cannot own your Practices, or ſubmit to your Preceps) by concluding them none of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſt, becauſe none of your Memberſhip? Is the Body of Chriſt now ſhrunk and narrow'd into <hi>G. F</hi>'s Tribe of Members and Miniſters? are theſe the Lips only that preſerve Knowledg? are you the only Men that fear God and work Righteouſneſs? and muſt we forſake the inward Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony, to ask the Law from your Mouths? Can any thing be more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious and deſtructive to the Spirit of Life in Chriſt Jeſus than this Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine? or preſent it ſelf with greater horror and amazement to the minds of all rational and ſober Men, and all that truly fear God, that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction of a neceſſary ſubmiſſion to <hi>G. F.</hi> and his Tribe of Proſelytes, under the penalty of being no otherwiſe eſteemed than <hi>Heathens</hi> and <hi>Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels?</hi> Do not you in theſe things apparently cloath your ſelves with the Livery and Character of him who oppoſeth and exalteth himſelf above all that is called God, or worſhipped, by creating a Dominion over your Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and the movings of God in them, and claiming a Power to judg of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:45368:5"/>all Differences, preſcribing Rules and Orders, and putting Yokes upon the Necks of your Diſciplles, to the ſtifling of their Conſciences, wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Peace, and deſtroying that Liberty wherewith Chriſt hath made them free? If this be the Spirit which you at preſent ſtand in, (as your ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral forementioned Papers do plainly import) I dare boldly challenge all that have gone before you, from the <hi>Pope</hi> himſelf downward, to all Sects and Opinions extant in the World, to produce, if they can, a greater In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of ſwelling Soveraignty over the Minds and Conſciences of Men, than you have erected. And certainly had you a Secular Power but framed and fitted to your Rule, Eccleſiaſtical Supremacy, the World would ſoon feel, that the Finger of your Church-Cenſures, would bear an equal weight (at leaſt) with the Loins of thoſe Perſecutors which have bin your Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors. Now (all this conſidered) can you in ſoberneſs conceive that this frame of Spirit (in that abſolute Dominion which you claim to your ſelves over all others) will render you the Healers of our Breaches, and the Reſtorers of our Paths of Peace? Can you think that this Arbitrary and Haughty Government, will invite the Nations and Languages of all Sects and Opinions, to lay hold on your Skirts, with deſire to be led by you, becauſe the Lord is with you? Or do they not rather with dread and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror behold you, while you ſo heavily impoſe upon others in ſuch Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances and Indifferencies, wherein the Kingdom of God doth not conſiſt, and make thoſe Rules and Preſcriptions of equal value with Divine Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions? Witneſs the Hat, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the outward Garb impoſed upon your Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelytes; Your Set-times when to begin, and when to end your Religious Exerciſes (notwithſtanding your pretence of the immediate guidance of the Spirit); Your manner of greeting one another, with many things of the like Nature. To all which an exact conformity is required, upon the penalty of a Cenſure from <hi>G. F.</hi> and his Elderſhip.</p>
            <p>Now, dear Friends, can you (in the cool of the Day of God upon your Spirits) believe that this violent and rigid ſort of Practice, will render your Feet beautiful upon the Mountains? or will attract the Hearts of any wiſe or ingenuous People toward you? No ſurely, your experience may otherwiſe inform you, that ſince this violence (of <hi>Eſau</hi> againſt his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Jacob</hi>) hath appeared amongſt, you the Curſe of <hi>Babylon</hi> hath overtaken you, (<hi>Iſa.</hi> 47.9, to the end) even the loſs of Children and Widowhood, which will certainly come upon you in their perfection, as the Witneſs of God ariſeth amongſt thoſe that you have ſo heavily yok'd and burthened with your own invented Preſcriptions.</p>
            <p>I have done with you, when I have told you, That the Diſpenſations in which God adminiſters Himſelf to the World at this day, do moſt natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:45368:6"/>call for a more ſober, moderate, tender, and loving Spirit amongſt Chriſtians, than this wherein you are exerciſed. You cannot but obſerve how the Lord of Hoſts is pleading with the World in the dreadful Manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtations of his Power, (by <hi>Plague, Fire, Sword,</hi> &amp;c.) how He turns the Earth up-ſide down, and makes it reel to and fro like a Drunkard; and the Foundations of the World are out of Courſe, divided and broken, both in their Civil Policies, and Religious Practices. Fear, the Pit, and a Snare, have laid hold on the Inhabitants of the Earth, there is no Eſtabliſhment in their Paths, and the way of Peace they know not: Yea, this is the day of <hi>Jacob</hi>'s Troubles, and for the Diviſions of <hi>Reuben</hi> there are great ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Heart; God is now pleading in Judgment with the People that have bin called by his Name, ſearching <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> with Candles, (<hi>Zeph.</hi> 1.12, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) and Judgment is already begun at the Houſe of God; He is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to judg the Spiritual Pride and Exaltation, the Cruelty and Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, the Hypocriſy and Formality that hath mingled it ſelf with all the fair and beautiful Profeſſions of thoſe that have bin called <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> And what will you ſay (my Friends) if in <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Skirts be found the Blood of the Souls of the poor Innocent? (<hi>Jer.</hi> 2.34, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) Now if this be the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Work of the Almighty at this day (as certainly all that are not either blinded with Carnal Intereſt, or lull'd into a formal Security, muſt needs acknowledg); Can you yet be ſo vainly confident, as to perſwade your ſelves that nothing of this Evil ſhall come near your Borders, whilſt the Arrows of God's Judgments fly ſo thick in the World, and ſtick ſo deep in the Hearts and ſides of all, both Civil and Religious Intereſts? Are you, and your Impoſing Tribe, the only Men that muſt eſcape, when the whole World is to be ſet on Fire, yea, the very Heavens of Profeſſors are to be burnt up, and nothing to be left alive in us, but what can lie down in thoſe Flames? Is there nothing, think ye, in or amongſt your People that is for Judgment? Or, is this a time for you to build (and raiſe a Name to your ſelves) when God is deſtroying? to contend for outward Rule and Dominion over others, when God is pleading his own Royal Prerogative? to fit in judgment over the Conſciences of your Brethren, when the Judg ſtands at the Door? Or are ye ſo regardleſs of the prints and footſteps of the Almighty in his preſent Providences, that ye ſay in you Hearts, with that Evil Servant, <hi>The Lord delays his coming?</hi> and fall to ſmiting your fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Servants with the Tongue and Fiſt of Wickedneſs, wounding and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching them with your bitter and ſevere Cenſures, thinking (with the evil Husbandmen) therewith to kill and ſlay the Heir, the Seed of God in Man, that muſt rule and reign? Surely (my Friends) the tempeſtuous Storms of Wrath and Indignation that you ſee falling upon the World,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:45368:6"/>do earneſtly call for a more mild and ſober Spirit amongſt you than this: <hi>Let</hi> therefore <hi>your Moderation be known to all men; the Lord is at hand.</hi> If you would be a Bleſſing to the World in your Generation, learn firſt to judg and condemn your ſelves: Caſt off your Judging, Cenſuring, and impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Spirit, and give the Witneſs of God in every one its juſt Right, its due Scope and Latitude, and uſurp not Authority over it: Take not upon you to be Lords over God's Heritage; let the Bowels of your Love and Tenderneſs be drawn out and extended towards the Meaſure of God in all Men of every Religion, in forbearance and forgiveneſs to the whole World. Follow Peace in the Spirit of Love with all Men, and Holineſs, without which no Man ſhall ſee God. Give <hi>Chriſt</hi> his Prerogative in Spirituals, He muſt and will have it; Give <hi>Caeſar</hi> his due in Temporals, who may of undoubted right challenge it. Thus if you can commend your ſelves to God and the World, ye ſhall be the Joy of this Generation; all good Men will be drawn out in an earneſt imitation of your Purity, while the violent and wicked ſhall ſtand mute, and be ſtruck dumb at your modeſt Patience and Meekneſs; you ſhall never want either inward Peace, or outward Freedom, but ye ſhall enter into Peace, and reſt in your Beds, each one walking in his Uprightneſs. This (my dear Friends) is the Teſtimony, in which I long to meet you, and which will juſtly provoke the hearty embraces of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your true Friend in Love to ſerve you, <hi>R. R.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT of ſome BOOKS lately publiſhed of Mr. <hi>ROBERT RICH's.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">I. Hidden Things brought to light, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. His Epiſtles to the Seven Churches, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. to the <hi>Roman Catholick;</hi> 2. the <hi>Epiſcopal Proteſtant;</hi> 3. the <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> 4. the <hi>Independent,</hi> 5. the <hi>Anabaptiſt;</hi> 6. the <hi>Quaker;</hi> 7. the <hi>Church of the Firſt-Born.</hi> Containing his Teſtimony to Gods <hi>Approbation</hi> of the <hi>Good,</hi> and <hi>Aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation</hi> to the <hi>Evil</hi> in all <hi>Perſuaſions.</hi> Sold by <hi>Fr. Smith,</hi> at the Elephant and Caſtle in <hi>Cornhil</hi> near the Royal Exchange.</p>
            <p n="3">III. Abſtracts of ſeveral Letters, treating moſt of Spiritual Matters, tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to Poſterity, and recommended to the ſober and ſerious Enquirer, for promoting of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Love</hi> amongſt all ſorts of People, without reſpect of Perſons, Parties, or Sects. Together with a friendly Letter of Dr. <hi>Jer. Taylor</hi>'s to <hi>R. R.</hi> in Anſwer to one of his. Sold by <hi>Benjamin Billingſly</hi> at the <hi>Printing-Preſs</hi> in <hi>Cornhil</hi> under the Royal Exchange.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
